Finding Aid for the John Fulton “Uncle Remus” Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
John Fulton “Uncle Remus” Collection
1878–1928
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0159
2.94 Linear Feet
Biography/History
John Fulton (1837-1932} was born a slave on Andrew Jackson's Hermitage estate in Hermitage, Tennessee and died in Nashville.
In 1885, he came to Vanderbilt University to serve the famous IV Club, composed of four bachelor professors who kept house together in Wesley Hall. They were: William L. Dudley, Austin H. Merrill, J. T. McGill and W. T. Magruder. James H. Kirkland destined to become chancellor, later joined the group. As members of the group married, there remained only William L. Dudley, and he became his private servant. He resided in a small room in the basement of Wesley Hall, where he entertained the students by playing his guitar, singing ancient ballads, and reading Uncle Remus stories to the students, which is how he acquired his nickname. Fulton's room was a storehouse of memories. He collected photographs from the students and literally papered all four walls with the photographs. Those that would not fit on the wall were stored in trunks. And, the amazing thing is that he could tell you the names of every student.
In 1914, after Dudley's death, he became the caretaker for Mrs. R. F. Jackson. His duties kept him at that place during the day, but when night came he went back to his little room in the basement of Wesley Hall until the fire in February 1932. He died shortly after in April 1932.
In 1975, the Alumni Office transferred this collection to Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
This 2.21 linear feet collection contains two series: Series I contains two postcards, an election campaign card, four guest registers, and a newspaper clipping. Series II contains 400 plus photographs, some with inscriptions. All have been numbered and scanned into the photograph database. Except for some images at the end, the photographs are alphabetical by person. When known graduation year is included.
- Series I – General
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - from W. R. Austin - postcard, February 21, 1911 (Box 1)
  - from Beverly W. Allen - postcard, August 27, 1928 (Box 1)
- Election Campaign Card
  - William C. Levere for State Representative, November 6, 1906 (Box 1)
- Guest Registers
  - 1909 – 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1910 – 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 [contains slips of paper with guest signatures] (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clipping
  - Unidentified Group Photograph, n.d. (Box 1)
- Series II – Photographs
- Adams to Davidson (Box 1)
  Adams, W. G. n.d.
  Akin, Grover J. Alumnus 1913
  Anderson, Stonewall n.d.
  Anthony, Walter Alumnus 1905
  Armistead, George Harrison, Jr. Alumnus 1914-1916
  Arterbury, Roy L. Alumnus 1916-1917
  Arthur, Robert n.d.
  Barnett, Robinson Ira (2) Alumnus 1904
  Baskerville, Charles Read Alumnus 1896
  Bates, William Hunt Alumnus 1894
  Battin, Samuel Jackson Alumnus 1897
  Bayliss, Bronson B. Alumnus 1899
  Beauchamp, William Benjamin Alumnus 1893
  Bernard, Adolph Arthur Alumnus 1906
  Betterton, Thomas Crews Alumnus 1892
  Bettis, E. S. Alumnus 1893
  Bishop, David Horace Alumnus 1897
  Black, McKendree M. Alumnus 1892
  Blanks, Anthony Faulkner Alumnus 1850-1860
  Blanton, William Henson Alumnus 1910
  Blevins, Wilson Alumnus 1878-1879
  Borner, John O'Neill Alumnus 1913
  Bowers, Paul C. Alumnus 1910-1913
  Boyd, Dallas n.d.
  Boyd, George n.d.
  Boyd, George McAdory Alumnus 1903
  Bradsford, Henry Erwin Alumnus 1908
  Branham, Boiling Sasnett Alumnus 1914
  Brewer, Edward Cage Alumnus 1911
  Briley, Henry Pope Alumnus 1899
  Britt, Leon n.d.
  Britt, — and Baby n.d.
  Brown, Doswell Parrish Alumnus 1899-1903
  Brown, Oswald Eugene Alumnus/Faculty 1917
  Brown, W. C. Foskette Alumnus 1916
  Bryant, — and — Decamfleolis n.d.
  Burleson, Daniel Downs Alumnus 1909
  Burr, Alfred Hamlin Alumnus 1914
  Cameron, Irvin Turner Alumnus 1903
  Campbell, Clyde Kenner Alumnus 1907
  Campbell, H. L. n.d.
  Carey, J. Franklin Alumnus 1903
  Carr, Peter Herbert Alumnus 1898
  Carre, Henry Beach Faculty 1898
  Carter, H. M. Alumnus 1897
  Chenault, Frederick Raymond Alumnus 1910-1912
  Chiles, T. H. Alumnus 1899
  Chilton, Cladius Lysias Alumnus 1902
  Christian, William Asbury Alumnus 1892
  Clark, Valentine Cornelius Alumnus 1904
  Clark, Warren n.d.
  Clifton, John W. Alumnus 1903
  Cobb, Robert Linah Alumnus 1906
  Coleman, Felix H. Alumnus 1895
  Coleman,----- n.d.
  Comer, Harry Fulcher Alumnus 1912
  Compton,----- n.d.
  Connell, Clarence P. Alumnus 1902-1906
  Connell, William Phillips Alumnus 1897
  Cook, Cassie Bell Alumnus 1916
  Cook, Osgood Francis Alumnus 1892
  Cornelius, Rufus Thomas Alumnus 1907-1910
  Corum, Jesse Maxwell Alumnus 1906
  Cothran,----- 1897
  Creighton, John H. Alumnus 1894-1895
  Crockett, Edmond Irving Alumnus 1888
  Crowe, Fletcher Standefer Alumnus 1915
  Crutchfield, "Babe" Alumnus 1900
  Cude, Harold Eugene Alumnus 1911
  Cuninggim, Jesse Lee Alumnus/Faculty 1895
  Curlin, Zachary Henry Alumnus 1914
  Curtiss, Lyle Raymond Alumnus 1908-1912
  Dailey, Henry Jackson Alumnus 1899-1900
  Daniel, John Jr. Alumnus 1920-1921
  Davidson, Donald Alumnus/Faculty 1916
- Davis to Holderness (Box 2)
  Davis, James Wendel Alumnus 1890
  Dean, Charles Herrn on Alumnus 1905
  Dempsey, Elam Frank Alumnus 1906
  Dent, Wilbur Tillett Alumnus 1911-1916
  Dentón, Guy Tresslen Alumnus 1906-1913
  Dickenson, M. U. n.d.
  Dickinson,-----/Berie,----- n.d.
  Dillard, J. H. n.d.
  Dobbs, Hoyt McWhorter Alumnus 1904
  Dortch, F. W. Faculty 1898
  Doss, Washington LaFayette, Jr. Alumnus 1890
  Dowman, Charles E. Jr. n.d.
  Dozier, Howard Douglas Alumnus 1908
  Draper, Walter Scott, Jr. Alumnus 1901
  Duckworth, Robert Pierce Alumnus 1898
  Dudley, William L. Faculty n.d.
  Dudley, William L./Freddie Moore Faculty n.d.
  Dye, John Sinclair Alumnus 1900
  Eakes, Marvin n.d.
  Enochs, Marvin Smith Alumnus 1899
  Evans,----- n.d.
  Fant, Lester Glenn Alumnus 1897-1899
  Farrell, William Elliston Alumnus 1891
  Fields, Robert G. Alumnus 1915
  Fifer,----- n.d.
  Fix, Joseph Wood Alumnus 1922
  Follin, Gerald Webb Alumnus 1914
  Ford, William Vernon Alumnus 1911
  Frantz, Frank Flavius/J. Mack Jenkins Alumnus 1902-1910
  Frierson, John Dawson Alumnus 1911-1912
  Gamble, Foster Kirk Alumnus 1907
  Gannaway, Herbert/Bethel Long Alumnus 1904
  Gannaway, Herbert Alumnus 1901-1904
  Gantt, Nicholas J. Jr. Alumnus 1901-1903
  Gardiner, S. Vaughn Alumnus 1899
  Gilbert,----- n.d.
  Givens, Claude Preston Alumnus 1912-1914
  Glasgow, Benjamin Bascom Alumnus 1904
  Glass, Henry Iverson Alumnus 1909-1914
  Godchaux, Frank Area Alumnus 1901
  Granbery, John Cowper Alumnus 1899
  Gray, Charles Walter Alumnus 1911
  Greer, C. H. Alumnus 1900
  Gunter, Arthur L. Alumnus 1912-1915
  Hager, Samuel E. Alumnus 1893
  Halliburton, Wesley Alumnus 1891
  Harris, William Irion 03-22-1898
  Harvey,----- 1897
  Hawk, John Crisman Alumnus 1905
  Hawkins, Eugene Alumnus 1895
  Heflin, John James Alumnus 1905
  Henry, Waights Gibbs Alumnus 1902
  Herbert, T. Grigsby Alumnus 1893
  Herndon, Virgil Crook Alumnus 1913
  Hirst, Mr. and Mrs. n.d.
  Holcombe, Armstead Richardson Alumnus 1899
  Holderness, James Sidney Alumnus 1905-1906
- Holland to McKenzie (Box 3)
  Holland, Richard Marion Alumnus 1906
  Holman, Harvey Thomas Alumnus 1902
  Holmes, William Walter Alumnus 1903
  Hornback, James Matthew Alumnus n.d.
  Hounshell, Charles Gideon Alumnus 1899
  Howard, William James Alumnus 1899-1902
  Huffman, Chester Clinton Alumnus 1915
  Hughes, Urban Becker Alumnus 1912
  Hughes, William Wightman Alumnus 1902
  Hunter, James Duncan Alumnus 1907-1910
  Hunter, J. R. Alumnus 06-01-1893
  Irion, J. Witt Alumnus n.d.
  James, John Caller Alumnus 1903-1905
  Jenkins, J. Michael Jr. Alumnus 03-19-1904
  Johnston, — n.d.
  Johnston, Mercer G. Alumnus 08-01-1898
  Jones, Elliott H. Alumnus 1891
  Jones, Ernest Scott Alumnus 1897
  Jones, Frank Alumnus n.d.
  Jones, Henry H. Alumnus 1914
  Jones, Herbert V. Alumnus 1901
  Jones, Paul Mitchell Alumnus 1885
  Joyner, Nicholas E. Alumnus 1897
  Kern, David H. Alumnus 1895
  Kern, Paul Bentley Alumnus 1902-1905
  Kirkland, Charles B. Alumnus 1890
  Lander, Frank Dunnington Alumnus 1912
  Langley, Joseph D. Alumnus 1897
  Lawrence, — Alumnus n.d.
  Lipscomb, Horace Swift Jr. Alumnus 1901
  Locke, William Thomas and Edwin Mims, Albert Robins Alumnus n.d.
  Logan, Will Gordon Alumnus 1913
  Long, Lemul Rix Alumnus 1900
  Long, William Bethel Mulberry School, Principal Alumnus 1899-1904
  Lovelace, Griffin M. Alumnus 1897
  Lund, Robert Leathan Alumnus 1895-1897
  Luter, Clark Allen Alumnus 1914
  Lutz, Albert Simion Alumnus n.d.
  Magruder, William T. Alumnus 1894
  Mahoney, James Owen Alumnus 1894-1896
  Major, — Alumnus n.d.
  Marshall, George G. Alumnus 1902
  Matthews, William Kennon Alumnus 1895
  McCulloch, James E. Alumnus 1901
  McGill, Elsa n.d.
  McGill, John Thomas Faculty 1879-1882
  McGlothin, Harvey Love Alumnus 1913
  Mclntyre, Marvin H. and Olin West Alumnus 1898
  McKellor, Idus Eugene Alumnus 1906
  McKenzie, Edward Alumnus 1899
- McLaurin to Shannon (Box 4)
  McLaurin, David E. Alumnus 1904
  McNeilly, Albert S. Alumnus n.d.
  Merrill, Austin H. Faculty 1996-1900
  Merriman, Lucius S. Alumnus 06-1889
  Merritt, Daniel Tatum Alumnus 1898
  Miller, Hugh Hedges Alumnus 1898
  Miller, Samuel Marvin Alumnus 1902-1905
  Miller, Victor Irvin Alumnus 1897
  Mitchell, James B. Alumnus 1900
  Montgomery, Riley B. Alumnus 1923
  Moore, Frederick W. Faculty 1893-1911
  Morgan, George Allen Alumnus 1897
  Morgan, Joseph J. Alumnus 1899
  Morgan, William Henry Alumnus 1913
  Morrison, Jesse Ray Alumnus/Faculty 1912
  Nance, Walter Buckner Alumnus/BOT 1893-1904
  Naylor, G. R. Alumnus 1912
  Neblett, John Walter Alumnus 1900
  Nellums, Marrus Elmo Alumnus 1912
  Nelson, Oscar Gustaf Alumnus 1911-1915
  Nichols, John Alumnus 1904
  Nishikawa, Tamaño Suke Alumnus 1902
  Nolen, Fendall C. Alumnus 1899
  O'Connor, Myles Powers Alumnus 1897
  O'Dell, Edson Kenny Alumnus 1902
  Perry, John Wiley Alumnus 1891
  Perry, Prentiss M. Alumnus 1913-1915
  Perryman, Lewis and Benjamin P. Gilbert Alumnus 1911
  Plater, Richard C. Alumnus 1892
  Porter, Philip H. Alumnus 1892
  Porter, Robert Edwin Alumnus 1903
  Powell, Nathan Alumnus 1894
  Powell, Paul Shell Alumnus 1910-1913
  Prickett, John Wiley Alumnus 1900
  Pritchett, Granville Morrison Alumnus 1896-1900
  Proctor, Creasy Kinnons, Lemuel Edgar Wiggins, J. Howard Books Alumnus 1912
  Purcell, Claire Alumnus 1910-1916
  Ragsdale, Clifton A. Alumnus 1915
  Rapp, J. Carlisle Alumnus 1907
  Ray, John Allen Alumnus 1903
  Rector, Giles Carroll Alumnus 1893-1897
  Reynolds, H. A. Alumnus 1900
  Ricks, William Benjamin Alumnus 1894
  Roberson, Horace Maxey Alumnus 1903-1906
  Roberts, W. J. Alumnus 1892
  Rodriquez, P. Alphonso Faculty 1894
  Ryang, Ju Sam Alumnus 1913
  Saner, Dorothy Lee 1895
  Saner, Robert E. Lee Alumnus 1896
  Sawyer, John Granberry Alumnus 1913-1920
  Schoolfield, John Ralph Alumnus 1910
  Scott, Earl Francis Alumnus 1903-1906
  Self, William Dennis Alumnus 1908
  Seward, Douglas C. Alumnus 1916-1924
  Shackleford, John Walter Alumnus 1903
  Shannon, E. B. Alumnus 1900
- Sharp to Woodard (Box 5)
  Sharp, Joseph Casper Alumnus 1920
  Sibley, Hesse Bourbon Alumnus 1905
  Simmons, Walter Heinman Alumnus 1901-1903
  Simpson, Charles Jefferson Alumnus 1902
  Singleton, Frank Edus Alumnus 1902
  Smart, Richard Davis Jr. Alumnus 1900
  Smith, Frances Osgood 1906
  Smoot 1900
  Sneed, John B. Wardlaw 1899
  Spivey, Ludd Myrl Alumnus 1910
  Stephens and Charles Duncan Alumnus 1901-1910
  Stevenson, Alec Brock Alumnus 1916
  Stevenson, Henry Munn Alumnus 1900
  Stewart, Allen D. Alumnus 1911
  Stewart, John M. Alumnus 1912
  Stilz, Earl Bauer Alumnus 1914
  Stokes, Peter Alumnus 1891
  Strother, Charles Wesley Alumnus 1898
  Summers, Lemuel Chester Alumnus 1916-1919
  Swaim, John Carlisle Alumnus 1911-1913
  Terry, Benjamin Taylor Alumnus 1898-1900
  Thornburg, Charles Lewis Faculty 1881-1884
  Thrift, Charles Tinley 1905
  Tillett, Wilbur Fisk Faculty 1900
  Tucker, Willis Newton Alumnus 1898
  Turner, Edward Kimbrough Alumnus 1895
  Tuttle, Robert and Joe Maytubby Alumnus 1895
  Tyler, John Paul Alumnus 1904
  Underwood, E. Marvin Alumnus 1900-1902
  Vaughn, — n.d.
  Vaughn, Harry S. Alumnus 1894
  Von Staur, Baron Alumnus 1909
  Vreeland, Walter Q. Alumnus 1891-1893
  Wailes, William L. C. 1906
  Warterfield, Cliff A. Alumnus 1895
  Washburn, Charles Campbell Alumnus 1892
  Waters, John R. 1900
  Watkins, — 1900
  Weatherford, Willis Duke Alumnus 1899-1907
  Weaver, Lester Alumnus 1916
  Weaver, Robert Angelo 1920
  Webb, Ernest Clay 1908
  Wendell, Jack Lunn Alumnus 1912
  Werlein, Ewing Alumnus 1910
  Werlein, Shepard Halsey Jr. Alumnus 1897
  West, Olin Alumnus 1895-1898
  White, Aaron Pancoast Alumnus 1917
  White, Robert Hiram Alumnus 1910
  Williams, Clark 1903
  Williamson, Charles Samuel 1902
  Willis, Paul Henning 1906
  Wilson, — 1900
  Wilson, Fred Taylor Alumnus 1908-1910
  Wimberly, Charles F. Faculty 1895
  Wolf, E. L. 1900
  Woodall, William Marvin Alumnus 1909
  Woodard, Fred Connell Alumnus 1916
- Woodson to Zimmerman, Unidentified, and Misc. (Box 6)
  Woodson, Thomas M. Alumnus 1916
  Wright, C. O. Faculty 1900
  Wynn, Samuel F. Alumnus 1893
  Yoe, John Howe Alumnus 1913-1914
  Yoe, Frances Cheely 1915
  Young, Wilbur Shelby Alumnus 1915
  Zimmerman, Ogburn, Chapman Alumni 1910
  Campus Scene - 1 n.d.
  Glee Club - 1 1900
  Wesley Hall Group - 1 1890s
  Unidentified - Group - 1 1890s
  Unidentified - Portraits - 4 1890s
  Unidentified - Portraits - 5 n.d.
  Unidentified - Portraits - 8 n.d.
  Unidentified - Portraits - 10 n.d.
  Unidentified - Portraits - 6 n.d.
  Unidentified - Portraits - 4 n.d.
  Cox, Eugene A. Alumnus 1899
  Crutchfield, Wallace Moss Alumnus 1900
  Alexander, Will Winton Alumnus 1912
  Fulton, John [as a child] Staff n.d.
  Hawley, Jim Alumnus 1892-1893
  Holderness, Marvin Early Alumnus 1902-1906
  Lewis, — n.d.
  Merrill, Austin H. Faculty 1886-1900
  Tolman, Herbert Cushing Faculty 1895-1923
  Fulton, John Staff 1914